<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The confe[s]sion of faith, subscrived by the Kingis Maiestie and his houshold togither vvith the copie of the bande, maid touching the maintenance of the true religion, the Kingis Majesties person and estate, &amp;c. : seuerally to be subscriued by all noblemen, barrons, gentlemen and otheris, according to the tenor of the acte of secret counsell, and commissionis therein contayned, as heirafter followeth.</title>
            <title>Scottish Confession of Faith (1581)</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11734</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22023</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S509</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22546838</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22546838</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25604</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11734)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25604)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1757:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The confe[s]sion of faith, subscrived by the Kingis Maiestie and his houshold togither vvith the copie of the bande, maid touching the maintenance of the true religion, the Kingis Majesties person and estate, &amp;c. : seuerally to be subscriued by all noblemen, barrons, gentlemen and otheris, according to the tenor of the acte of secret counsell, and commissionis therein contayned, as heirafter followeth.</title>
                  <title>Scottish Confession of Faith (1581)</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[34] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Waldegrave,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁶ C⁴ D² (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: t.p. stained and torn.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25604:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25604:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CONFES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SION OF FAITH, SVBSCRIVED BY THE KINGIS MAIESTIE and his Houſhold: TOGITHER VVITH THE COPIE OF THE BANDE, maid touching the maintenance of the true Religion, the Kingis Majeſties perſon and eſtate, &amp;c: Seuerally to be Subſcriued by all Noblemen, Barrons, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and otheris, according to the tenor of the acte of ſecret Counſell, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionis therein contayned, as heirafter fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>IOSHVA. 24. 25.</bibl> So Ioſhua made a couenant with the people the ſame day, and gaue them an ordinance and lawe in Shechem.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. KING. 11. 17.</bibl> And Iehojada made a couenant betweene the Lord, and the king and the people, that they ſhould be the Lordes people: likewiſe betweene the king and the people.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>ISAIAH. 44. 5.</bibl> One ſhall ſay I am the Lordes: another ſhalbe called by the name of Iaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob: and another ſhall ſubſcriue with his hand vnto the Lord, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>AT EDINBVRGH. Printed by ROBERT WALDE-GRAVE. Anno Dom. 1590.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="licence_to_print">
            <pb facs="tcp:25604:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:25604:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:25604:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PRIVILEDGE GRANTED to the Printer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lordis of the Secreit Counſell, grants and geuis licence &amp; Priuiledge be thir preſents, to ROBERT VVALDE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GRAVE, to Imprent, or cauſe to be imprentit, the Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oun of Faith, togidder with the generall Band, maid touching the maintenance of true Religioun, the Kingis Majeſties per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoun and Eſtate, and withſtanding of al forraine preparations and forcis tending to the troubill thairof. As alſo the Acte of ſecreit Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, Conteyning a Commiſſion to certaine Nobill men, Barons and vthers: for ſerching, ſeeking, apprehending and purſute of Papiſts, Ieſuits, Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Prieſtis and Excommunicate perſonis: with the like Commiſſioun to certaine Miniſters of Gods word, To receiue DE NOVO, the ſubſcriptions of al Nobill men, Barons, gentlemen and vthers his highnes liegis, of quhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeuer degree, to the ſaid generall Band. For the Imprinting of the quhilk Band, act of ſecret counſell, &amp; confeſſion forſaid, the ſaid lords decerns &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clars, that the ſaide Robert ſall not be callit or accufit, criminalie nor ciuilie, be any maner of way in time cumming. Nor incur naſkaith or danger in his perſon lands or guds. Bot the ſamin ſalbe countit &amp; eſtemit gud &amp; accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruice vnto his Majeſtie, tending to the aduancement of Gods glorie, &amp; common weale of this Realme. Exonering him be thir preſents, of all paine &amp; danger that he may incur thair throw for euer. Diſcharging be thir ſamin preſents, all and ſundrie Iudges and miniſters of his highnes lawis, &amp; vthers his Majeſties liegis and ſubjects qwhatſumever: Of al calling, accuſing, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, purſuing, or in anye wiſe proceeding againſt the ſaide Robert for the cauſe foreſaide, and of their offices in that part. Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriuit be the ſaide Lordis. At Edinburgh the xiij. day of March: The ȝeir of God, ane thouſand fiue hundred foureſcore nine ȝeiris.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25604:3"/>
            <head>ANESCHORT AND GENERALL CONFESSION OF THE TREVV CHRISTIANE FAITH and Religion, according to Godis worde and actis of Parliamentis, Subſcriued be the Kingis Maieſtie and his houſholde, with ſundrie vtheris, to the glorye of God and good example of all men. At E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinburgh the 28. day of Ianuarie: The ȝere of God. 1580. And the foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tene ȝere of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties raigne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E all, and euerie one of vs vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written proteſte, that after long and due examinatioun of our owne Conſciencis, in matters of true and fals Religion, are nowe throughly reſolued in the trueth, by the worde and ſpirit of God. And therefore we beleeue with our heartis, confeſſe with our mouthes, Subſcriue with our hands, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly affirme, before God and the whole worlde: That this onely, is the true Chriſtian Faith and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion pleaſing God, and bringing Saluation to man, quhilk is nowe by the mercie of God reuealed to the world, by the preaching of the bleſſed Euangell. And
<pb facs="tcp:25604:4"/> receaued, beleued and defended, by many &amp; ſundrie notable Kirkis and Realmes, but chiefely by the Kirk of Scotland, the Kings Maieſtie, and thre Eſtates of this Realme, as Gods eternall trueth, &amp; onely ground of our Saluation: as more particularly is expreſſed in the Confeſſion of our Faith, ſtabliſhed, and publictly confirmed by ſindrie Actis of Parliamentis, and now of a lang time hath bene opinly profeſſed by the kings Maieſtie, and whole bodie of this Realme, baith in burgh and land. To the quhilk Confeſſion and forme of Religion, we willingly agree in our Conſciencis in all pointis, as vnto Gods vndouted trueth and veritie, grounded onely vpon his written worde. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, we abhorre and deteſt all contrarie Religion and doctrine: But chiefely all kinde of Papiſtrie, in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and particular headis, euen as they are nowe dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and confuted by the worde of God and Kirk of Scotland: but in ſpecial, we deteſt and refuſe the vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped authoritie, of that Romaine Antichriſte vpon the Scriptures of God: vpon the Kirk, the ciuill magiſtrate &amp; conſcience of men. All his tyrannous Lawes made vpon in different things, againſt our Chriſtiane liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. His erroneous doctrine, againſt the ſufficiencie of the written worde, the perfection of the Lawe, the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſt, and his bleſſed Euangell. His corrupted doctrine concerning originall ſinne, our naturall ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie and rebellion to Gods Lawe. Our Iuſtification by Faith onely. Our imperfect ſanctification and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Lawe, the nature, number and vſe of the holy Sacraments. His fiue baſtard Sacraments, with al his rytis, ceremoneis, &amp; fals doctrine added to the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration
<pb facs="tcp:25604:4"/> of the true Sacraments without the word of God. His cruell Iudgement againſt Infants departing without the Sacrament, his abſolute neceſſitie of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, his blaſphemous opinion of Tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or reall preſence of Chriſts bodie in the elements, and receiuing of the ſame by the wicked, or bodies of men. His diſpenſationis with ſolemnet oathes, Periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and degrees of mariage forbidden in the worde: his crueltie againſt the innocent deuorced. His diuil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Meſſe, his blaſphemous Prieſtheid, his prophane ſacrifice for the ſinnes of the dead and the quick. His Canonization of men, calling vpon Angels, or Sanctis departed, worſhipping of Imagrie, Relicks, and Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, dedicating of Kirkis, Altars, Dayis, Vowes to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures. His Purgatorie, prayers for the dead, praying or ſpeaking in a ſtraunge language, with his Proceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis and blaſphemous Letanie, and multitude of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocats or Mediatouris. His manifolde Ordouris, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculare Confeſſion, his deſperat and vncertaine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, his generall and doutſome fayth, his Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factionis of men for their ſinnes, his Iuſtification by workis, OPVS OPERATVM, workis of Supereroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Meritis, Pardonis, Peregrinationis and ſtationis, his holy water, Baptizing of Bellis, Coniuring of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritis, Croſſing, Saning, Annointing, Coniuring, Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of Godis gude creatures, with the ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous opinion ioyned therewith, his VVorldly Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, &amp; wicked Hierarchie, his three ſolemned vowes, with all his ſhawelingis of ſundrie ſorts. His errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and bloodie decreis maide at Trent, with all the ſubſcryuers and approouers of that cruell and bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb facs="tcp:25604:5"/> bande, conjured againſt the Kirke of God. And fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, we deteſt al his vaine allegories, Rites, ſignes, &amp; traditions brought in the Kirk, without, or againſt the word of God, and doctrine of this true reformed Kirk. To the quhilk we joyne our ſelues willingly, in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Faith, Religion, Diſcipline, and vſe of the holy Sacraments, as liuely members of the ſame, in Chriſte our heade: promiſing and ſwearing, by the Greate Name of the Lord our God, that we ſhall continue in the obedience of the doctrine and diſcipline of this Kirk, and ſhall defende the ſame according to our vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and power, all the dayes of our liues, vnder the paines contained in the law, and danger baith of body and ſoule, in the daye of Gods fearefull judgement. And ſeeing that many are ſtirred vp by Satan, and that Romane Antichriſt, to promiſe, ſweare, ſubſcriue, and for a time, vſe the holy Sacraments in the Kirk deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, againſt their owne conſcience: minding hereby, Firſt vnder the externall cloake of religion, to corrupt and ſubuert ſecretly, Gods true religion within the Kirk, and afterward, when time may ſerue, to become open enemies and perſecuters of the ſame, vnder vaine hope of the Popes diſpenſation deuiſed againſt the worde of God, to his greater confuſion, and their double condemnation in the day of the Lorde Ieſus. We therefore, willing to take away al ſuſpition of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, and of ſic double dealing with God and his Kirk, proteſt, and call the ſearcher of all hearts for wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that our minds &amp; heartis, do fully agree with this our Confeſſion, promiſe, aith, and ſubſcription. So that we are not mooued for anye worldly reſpect, but
<pb facs="tcp:25604:5"/> are perſwaded onely in our conſcience, through the knawledge and lufe of Gods true religion, prentit in our heartis by the haly ſpirit, as we ſall anſwere to him in the day, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſall be diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And becauſe we perceiue, that the quietnes and ſtabilitie of our religion and Kirk, doth depend vpon the ſafetie and good behauiour of the Kings Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, as vpon ane comfortable Inſtrument of Gods mercie granted to this Countrie, for the maintaining of his Kirk, and miniſtration of juſtice amongſt vs. We proteſt and promiſe with our heartis vnder the ſame aithe, hand-writ, and paines, that we ſall defende his perſon and authoritie, with our geir, bodies and liues, in the defence of Chriſt his Euangell, libertie of our Countrie, miniſtration of Iuſtice, and puniſhment of Iniquitie, againſt all enemies within this Realme, or with out, as we deſire our God to be a ſtrong and merciful defender to vs in the day of our death, and comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. To whom with the father and the holy Spirite, be all honour and glorye Eternally, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="commission">
            <pb facs="tcp:25604:6"/>
            <head>THE KINGIS MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IESTIES CHARGE TO ALL COMMISSIONERS AND MI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters within this Realme.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eing, that we and our Houſhold, haue ſubſcryued &amp; geuen this publict Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our Faith, to the good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of our Subjectis. We commande and charge, all Commisſioners &amp; Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, to craue the ſame Confeſsion of their Parochinars, and procead againſt the refuſers, according to our Lawis and order of the Kirk, deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their names, and lawfull proceſſe to the Miniſters of our houſe, with all haſt and diligence, vnder the paine of xl. pound to be taken from their ſtipend, that we with the aduiſe of our Counſell, may take ordour with ſic proude contemners of God and our Lawes. Subſcryued with our hand. At Halyrudhous, 1580. the 2. day of March, the 14. yere of our raigne.</p>
            <div type="list_of_signatories">
               <pb facs="tcp:25604:6"/>
               <head>THE SVBSCRIBERS VNTO THE CONFESSION OF FAITH.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25604:7"/>
                  <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25604:7"/>
                  <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25604:8"/>
                  <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="oath">
            <pb facs="tcp:25604:8"/>
            <head>THE GENERALL BAND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee vnderſubſcriuand, conſidering the ſtrait linke and conjunctioun betuix the true &amp; chriſtian religion, preſently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſit within this our realme, &amp; ſouerane Lords eſtate and ſtanding, hauing baith the ſelf ſame frends &amp; common enemies, &amp; ſubject to the like event of ſtanding and decay: &amp; weying thair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall, the imminent danger threatned to the ſaid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, aſweill be forraine preparations for perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of that deteſtable conſpiracy againſt Chriſt and his Euangel, callit the halie league; as be outward and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtine practizes of the fauourers &amp; ſuppoſtis thairof amangis ourſelffis, quha now inanimat be the report of forrein powers repairing to this realm, begins mair planely to vtter &amp; profes their lang concelit euil mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the trueth, &amp; conſequently to the ſtanding of his Majeſtie our ſouerane Lorde: quhom they haue found and tryit to be ane conſtant and inflexible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour of the ſame. The preſeruation quhairof being dearer to vs, nor quhatſoeuer we haue deareſt in this life: and finding in his majeſtie, a maiſt honorable &amp; chriſtian reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to manifeſt himſelf to the warld, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> zealous and religious prince, quhilk he hes hithertils profeſſit, and to imploy the meanes &amp; power that God hath put into his hands, aſweill to the withſtanding of quhatſoeuer foreine force ſall mean within this Iland for alteration of the ſaid religioun, or endangering of the preſent ſtaite: as to the repreſſing of the inward e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies thairto amangis our ſelffs, linkit with thame in the ſaid antichriſtian league and confederacie. Haue thairfore in the preſence of Almichtie God, and with his Majeſties authorizing and allowance, faithfully
<pb facs="tcp:25604:9"/> promiſit &amp; ſolempnly ſworne, like as heirby we faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully &amp; ſolempnely ſweare &amp; promiſe, to take ane true cafauld and plaine part with his Majeſtie amangis our ſelffis, for diuerting of the appeirand danger threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the ſaid religioun, and his Majeſties eſtate and ſtanding depending thairvpon, be quhatſoeuer forein or inteſtine platts or preparations: And to that effect, faithfully, &amp; that vpon our trueths and honors, binds &amp; obliſhis vs to vthers: To conuene &amp; aſſemble our ſelffs publictly with our friends, in armes or in quiet maner, at ſick times and places as we ſalbe requirit be his proclamations, or be writ or meſſage direct to vs from his Majeſtie, or any hauing power from him: &amp; being conuenit and aſſemblit, To joyne and concur with the haile forceis of our friendis and fauourers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt quhatſoeuer foreine or inteſtine powers, or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts &amp; thair partakers, ſalariue or riſe within this Ila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or any part thairof, red die to defende or purſue, as we ſalbe authorized and conductit be his Majeſty, or any vther, hauing his power and comiſsion, to joyne and hald hand to the execution of quhatſoeuer meane or order ſalbe thocht meit be his Majeſty and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaill, for the ſuppreſsing of the papiſts, promotion of the true religion, and ſetling of his highnes eſtate and obedience in all the cuntries &amp; corners of this realme, to expone and hazard our liues, landis and gudis, and quhatſoeuer meane God hes lent vs, in the defence of the ſaid true &amp; chriſtian religion, &amp; his Majeſties per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and eſtate, againſt quhatſoeuer Ieſuitis and Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie or Meſſe preiſts, condamnit enemies to God and his Majeſtie, to thair vtter wracke and exterminion, according to the power grantit to vs be his highnes
<pb facs="tcp:25604:9"/> proclamation and Acts of parliament: To try, ſearch, and ſeik out all excommunicats, practizers, and vther papiſtes quhatſoeuer, within our bounds and ſhyres quhair we keip reſidence, delate thame to his highnes and his priuye Counſaill, and conforme vs to ſick di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, as fra time to time we ſall receiue fra his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and his Counſaill in thair behalfs, and ſpecially ſo many of vs as preſently ar, or heirafter ſalbe appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit commiſsioners in euery ſhyre, ſall followe, purſue and trauell be all meanes poſsible, to take and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend al ſick papiſtis, apoſtatis and excommunicatis, as we ſall receiue in writ from his Majeſty: and we, the remnant within that ſhyre, ſall concurre and aſsiſte with the ſaid commisſioners, with our haill friends &amp; forces to that effecte, without reſpecte of anye perſon quhatſoeuer. And generally to aſſiſt in the meane time and defend euery ane of vs ane vther, in al and quhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer quarrels, actions, debaits, mouit, or to be mouit againſt vs or any of vs, vpon action of the preſent band or vthers cauſes depending thairvpon, and cafauldly joyne in defence and purſute, againſt quhatſoeuer ſall offer or intend any injury or reuenge, againſt any ane of thame for the premiſſes: makand his cauſe and part that is purſued, al our partis. Notwithſtanding quhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer priuye grudge or diſpleaſures ſtanding betwix anye of vs, quhilk ſalbe na impediment or hinder to our ſaide eafaulde joyning in the ſaid common cauſe, bot to lye ouer and be miſknawne, till they be order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remouit and tane away be the order vnderſpecifier. To the quhilk time we, for the better furtherance of the ſaid cauſe and ſeruice, haue aſſurit, and be the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour heirof, euery ane of vs takand the burding on vs
<pb facs="tcp:25604:10"/> for our ſelffes and all that we may let, aſſures ilke v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be vnhurt, vnharmeit, or in any wiſe to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vadit be vs or any of our foreſaidis, for auld feid or new, vtherwayis nor be the ordinarie courſe of Lawe and juſtice: neyther ſall we, nor any of our forſaidis, make any prouocation of tumulte, trouble or diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to vthers in any ſort, as we ſall anſwere to God, &amp; vpon our honours and fidelitie to his Majeſtie. And for our furder and mare heartly vnion in this ſeruice, We are content and conſents, that al and quhatſoeuer our feids and variances fallin, or that may fall out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt vs, be within fourty dayis after the date heirof, amicably referrit and ſubmittit to ſeuin or fiue indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent freindis, choſen be his Majeſtie of our haill num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and be thair moderation and arbitrement com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponit and tane away. And finally, that we ſall neither directly nor indirectly, ſeperat or withdraw vs fra the vnion and fellowſhip of the remnent, be quhatſoeuer ſuggeſtion or priuat aduiſe, or be quhatſoeuer incident regard, or ſtay ſick reſolution, as be common delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſalbe tane in the premiſſes, as we ſall anſwer to God vpon our conſciences, &amp; to the world vpon our trueth and honours, and vnder the paine to be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit traytouris to God and his Majeſtie, and to haue loſt all honour, credit &amp; eſtimation in time cumming. In witnes quhairof his Majeſtie, in token of his appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, and protection promiſsit to vs in the premiſſes, and we be his authoriſing and allowance forſaid, haue ſubſcriued thir preſents with our hands.</p>
            <div type="list_of_signatories">
               <pb facs="tcp:25604:10"/>
               <head>THE SVBSCRIVERS VNTO THE GENERALL BAND.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25604:11"/>
                  <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25604:11"/>
                  <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25604:12"/>
                  <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25604:12"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="act">
            <head>THE ACT OF SE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CREIT COVNSAILL.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>AMES be the grace of God, King of Scottis:</signed>
               <salute>To our louitts,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Meſſengers, ourſchyriffes in that part, conjunctly &amp; ſeuerally, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſtitute greeting. Foraſmekle as be act of our parliament, Intitulate, ANENT THE TRYALL AND PVNISHMENT of the offence of the aduerſaries of the true religion preſently profeſſit within our realm. It is ſtatute and ordaint, that quhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer profeſſed and avowed Ieſuites, or Seminarie prieſts, ſhuld be found in any part of our realme, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſpace of ane moneth after the publication of the ſaid Act, quhilk wes duly publiſht vpon the 14. day of Auguſt, the ȝeir of God 1587. ȝeirs. Suld be taken, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, called, purſued, &amp; incur the paine of deid, and confiſcation of all their mouable guds, and quha euer wittingly or willingly ſuld receaue or ſupply any of thame thairefter, be the ſpace of three dayes &amp; three nychts togidder, or ſeuerally at three times, vpon cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine knawledge, that they are perſons of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, being lawfully &amp; orderly conuict of the ſame ſuld incur the tinſall of thair liuerents. And that they, as alſo the ſayers or hearers of the Meſſe, or propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Sacraments, or vthers perſons ſuſpecte to haue declined fra the true religion, or refuſing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort to the preaching of Gods worde, or quhatſoeuer perſon that ſuld be reaſoning, or diſperſing of buiks &amp; letters, preſume to perſuade any of our ſubjects, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline
<pb facs="tcp:25604:13"/> fra the profeſſion of the ſaid true religion: Being called to compeir and anſwer therevpon, before vs &amp; our priuie Counſaill, In caſe the perſons ſo dilated &amp; accuſed, or any of them, ſulde be founde culpable be our priuye Counſaill, or any fiue of them (our Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celler and Clarke of Regiſter being twa of that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) ather be the confeſſion of the ſaids perſons accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or be the depoſition of diuers famous witneſſes. Or gif the ſaidis perſons being called &amp; adjudged cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minally (in caſe we, &amp; the Lords of our priuie counſel ſall ſo thinke gude) and were found culpable &amp; guilty of the premiſes: That they thairthrow, ſuld incur the pane of tinſell of al thair mouable guds, togidder with the liferents of al thair lands &amp; liuings quhatſoeuer, to be vptaken &amp; imployed to our awne vſes, &amp; na wayes diſponit to the perſons that ſuld be conuict or fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue for the cauſe foreſaid: as the ſaid Act of our Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in the ſelfe proports. And becauſe we and our eſtates, quhilk conuenit at Halirudehous, vpon the 27 day of Iuly. The ȝeir of God, 1588. ȝeirs, perceiued be gude experience, the inconuenient that followed, throwe default of nonputting of the ſame Act to due execution, and that thairthrow the ſaidis Ieſuitis, and ſeminarie preiſts diſdained our ſaid Acts, &amp; continued in ſeducing and perſwading of diuers of our nobilitie and vtheris our gude ſubjectis, to decline fra the ſaide true and chriſtian Religion, and to practize the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and trouble of our Eſtate. Thairfore be ane vther Act &amp; ordinance maid be vs, our ſaids nobilitie, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaill and eſtates, quhilk conuenit the ſaid 27. day of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: certaine perſons ſpecially expreſſed thairin were nominate, elected and conſtitute our Commiſſioners,
<pb facs="tcp:25604:13"/> and Iuſticeis in that parte, within the boundis of our ſchirefdoms ſtewartries, bayliereis, Burrowis and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties vnder mentioned: Like as to thame conjunctly &amp; ſeuerally, within the bounds ſpecially limited to tham were giuen our full power and commiſſion. All and ſundrie Ieſuits, and Seminarie prieſts: as namely, M. Iames Gordon, father brother to the Erle of Huntley, maſter Edmond Hay, brother to the gudeman of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginche, M. William Creichton, M. Alexander Mack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quhirry, Gilbert Browne ſomtime Abbot of New ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bay, M. Mark Ker ſonne to Robert Ker elder, burges of our burgh of Edinburgh, and certain vthers of that profeſſion, incaſe they ſuld nocht depart forth of our realme, and enter thameſelfes to the Proueſt of our ſaid burgh of Edinburgh, til haue bene ludged, quhile occaſion ſeruit to tranſport thame according to our proclamation publiſht to that effect. And als all and ſundry our rebels, remaining at the Horne, for ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or ſick vthers odious crimes, and all ſornars, bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gandis and maiſterfull vagaboundis. To ſearch, ſeike, take and apprehende, and either to bring and preſent thame before our juſtice and his deputes in our burgh of Edinburgh, or then our ſaide juſtices and commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners thameſelffs, to put the ſaids Ieſuits and Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Prieſts, and vtheris aboue written, to the knaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ane asſiſe for the ſaids wicked and vnlawfull practizes and attempts, and contemptuus diſobeying and contrauening of our laws and acts of parliament, and vther odious crimes committed be thame, and as they ſuld be fundin culpable or innocent, to miniſter juſtice vpon thame, conforme to the lawes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetude of our realme, courte or courts to this effect
<pb facs="tcp:25604:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:25604:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:25604:15"/> to ſet, begin, affirme, hald and continue deputis vnder thame, with clerks, ſerjands, dempſtars and all vthers officers and members of court neidfull: to make, cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, ſubſtitute and ordaine Asſiſe ane or ma, to that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, ilke perſon vnder the paine of fourty poundis, to ſummond, warne, cheeſe, and cauſe be ſworn, vnlawis, amerchiaments and eſcheits of the ſaidis courts: to aske, lift and raiſe, and for the ſame gif neid beis to poind and diſtrenzie, compt, reckoning and paiment to vs and our treaſurour in our name in our checker to make: quhairin the neceſſarie expenſſes to be maid in the execution of our ſaid commiſſion, is appointed to be defeaſit and allowed. And incaſe the ſaidis Ieſuitis and Seminarie prieſtis, and vthers aboue ſpecified, ſall happen to flee to houſes and ſtrenthis, To aſſege and perſue thame thairin, raiſe fire, and vſe all force &amp; war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ingyne for recouerie thairof. And gifit ſall happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any of tham, or any asſiſting &amp; concurring with tham to be hurt, ſlaine or mutilat, or any wracke, diſtruction of houſe or gudes to be done: the ſame to be impute for na crime nor offence, to our ſaids Iuſticers &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misſioners, or perſons asſiſting thame in the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on heirof: nor they nor nane of thame, to be called or accuſed for the ſame, criminally nor ciuilie, be any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of way in time cumming: Exonering thame of all action and crime, that may be moued and intended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thame or any of tham for the ſame, and diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging all oure judges and miniſteris of our lawis of all calling, outlawing or any wiſe proceding againſt tham thairfore, and of thair officers in that part for euer. Mairouer with power to the ſaids juſtices &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>misſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to enquire, quhat feidis or variance ſtandis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb facs="tcp:25604:15"/> any parties inhabitant within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhyres &amp; bounds appointed to thame, &amp; quha wer the maiſt able &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t freinds, to be imployed for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poning &amp; away taking thairof. And to require &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to trauel to that effect: And the perſons ſtanding at variance, to ſubmit thamſelfs, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moderation &amp; arbitrement of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaids indifferent freinds, according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> effect &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the generall band, ſubſcriued be vs and diuers of our eſtates: or incaſe of refuſe or delay, to certifie the ſame to vs &amp; our counſaill with al conuenient di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, that ſick further order mycht be tane thair a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, as apperteinit. And to moue certain of the maiſt zealous &amp; worthie perſons in euery parochin, to take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oure commiſſion, for execution of our Act of Parliament maid for puniſhment of ſtrange &amp; idil beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and reliefe of the pure and impotent: as alſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainit and commanded our ſaidis commiſſioners and juſticers, to proclame, &amp; cauſe make wapponſhawings of al fenſable perſons in the bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds particularly limitat to tham, &amp; to charge thame to conuene in armes at al occaſions neidfull, for defence of the cuntrie, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of all outwarde and domeſtick invaſion, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the danger of the profeſſors of Gods true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or trobling of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon quietnes of our realm: And further to charge &amp; require all our gude ſubjects to concur and aſſiſt thame in the execution of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, vnder the panes contened in the acts of our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: And further vnder the pane to be repute, hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, eſtemed and purſued, as hinderers of our ſeruice, airt, and pertakers with the forſaids rebellious &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient perſons, in thair vngodly and wicked deids, And that our ſaids commiſſioners &amp; juſticers do thair exact diligence for execution of the premiſes, as they
<pb facs="tcp:25604:16"/> &amp; euery ane of them, wil anſwer to vs vpon their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, at their vttermoſt charge &amp; peril. And further vnder the pane of ane thouſand pounds, to be paid be euery ane of thame that ſalbe founde remiſſe or negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent heirin, as the ſaid acte of our ſecreit counſaill, of the date forſaid, at mair length proports. Quhilk, with the ſaid act of our parliament, &amp; vthers acts, ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and commisſions paſt, and geuen for executing of the ſame acts, againſt the ſaid Ieſuits, Seminary prieſts and excommunicate perſons: the ſaide Lords of our ſecreit counſail, in our name, ratifies, approues and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daines the ſame, to be put to further execution in all points, conforme to the tenour thairof, with ſick expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as conueniently may be. And becauſe there is certain of the Noble men, Barrons and vthers expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed commisſioners, in the ſaid act of our ſecreit coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaill, maid vpon the ſaid 27. day of Iuly foureſcore ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ȝeirs, that ſen the making thairof, ar departed this life, vthers diſeaſed in thair bodies, and ſome abſent forth of our realme, and in vther partis far diſtant fra the bounds, within the quhilk commisſion wes geuin to thame, be reaſon of thair reſidence thairin for the time, ſo that at this preſent, they may not conuenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſe and execute our ſaide commisſion, with ſick ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition as is requiſit. Thairfore the ſaids Lords of our ſecreit counſaill, at the humble and earneſt deſire of the generall aſſembly of the Kirk, preſently conuenit, hes thought gude, concluded and ordainit, That our ſaid commisſion and acts forſaid, ſalbe put in due and full execution, be the perſons reſpectiue after follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, giuen in be tham in roll, within the liberties, ſchy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifdoms, ſtewartries and baylieries particularly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned:
<pb facs="tcp:25604:16"/> Thay are to ſay, the Proveſts and baylies of euery citie and burgh, juſticers and commisſioners within the ſelfe, and liberties of the ſame. And for the cuntrie to landwart, Robert earle of Orknay, within the bounds of our ſhyrifdome of Orknay, George earl of Caithnes, Coline Mackenzie of Kintaill, Thomas Fraſer of Knokky, Andro Monro of Dowachartie, An gus Williamſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mackintoſh in Termet, and Iohn Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quhart tutor of Cromartie within the bounds of our ſhyrifdoms of Innernes and Cromartie. Iohn Camp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel of Caddell our ſhyriff of Narne. Hucheon Ros of Kilrawak, &amp; Iohn Hay of Lochloy, within the bounds of our ſhyrifdom of Narne, Iames earle of Murray, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trik Dumbar ſhyriff wardatare of Elgin and Fores, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Innes of that ilke, Iohn Grant of Frewchy, Iames Dumbar of Tarbert, &amp; Dauid Dumbar of Grangehill within the boundis of our ſhyrifdoms of Elgin &amp; Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. William earl of Morton ſhyrif wardatare of Bamff Alexander L. Salton, &amp; Walter Ogiluy of Findlatter within the bounds of our ſhyrifdome of Bamff. Iohn maiſter of Forbes, William Forbes of Corſſe, Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Irwing of Drum, Iames Creichto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Frendraucht Alexander Seton of Meldrum, Iohn Gordon of Pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurg, William Keith of Ludquharne and William Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Foverne, within the bounds of our ſhyrifdome of Aberdene. William earle of Angus, George earle Marſhall, Robert L. of Altree, Andro L. Dingwell, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander Straton of Lourenſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Iohn Strauchauchine of Thornton, Iohn Wiſchart of Pettarro, &amp; Iohn Ram<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſey of Balmane, within the bounds of our ſhyrifdome of Kincardin. Iohn L. Hammilton, Thomas maiſter of Glammis, Patrick maiſter of Graye, Dauid Lindſey of
<pb facs="tcp:25604:17"/> Edzel, Iames Skrimgeour of Dudop co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtable of Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, &amp; George Haliburton of Pitcur, within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bounds of our ſhyrifdom of Forfair. Iohn earl of Athoil, Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane Campbell of Glenurquhart, Thomas Stewart of Garntully, Alexander Blair of Bathyok, William Mon criff of that ilke, and Patrick Ogiluy of Inche Martin within the bounds of our ſhyrifdome of Perth, Stor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>month and Dunkeld. Iohn Murray of Tullibardin, Iohn Stirling of Keir, and M. Iohn Halden of Glen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negeis, within the bounds of our ſtewartries of Strath erne, Menteith &amp; Diocie of Dunblane. William earl of Morton, Alexander commendatar of Culros, Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Menteith of Kerſſ, &amp; Robert Bruce of Clakman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nane, within the boundis of our ſhyrifdomes of Clak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannane and Kinroſſ. Andro earl of Rothes our ſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rif of Fyffe. Iames L. Lindſay of the Byres, M. William Lundy of that ilk, Andro Wood of Largo, and Dauid Carnegy of Culluthy, within the bounds of our ſhirif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Fyffe. Iohn earle of Mar, William L. Leuing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton, Alexander Foreſter of Gardin, and Iohn Leuing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton ȝounger of Donypace, within the bounds of our ſhyrifdom of Striuiling. Georg Dundas of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ilk, Nicol Cornwal of Ballinhard &amp; Dauid Du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>das of Preiſtſinch within the bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of our ſhirifdom of Lynlythqw. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chibald Naper of Marcheinſton, Alexander Fairly of Braid &amp; Patrik Monype<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny of Pilrig, within the bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of our ſhyrifdom of Edinburgh. Willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>erl of Angus, Francis earl Bothuell, William Lord Hay of Ȝeſter, Sir Iohn Maitland of Thirlſtane knight our Chancelour, and Alexander Hume of Northberuicke, within the bounds of the conſtabularie of Hadington and Dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar. Sir Iames Hume of Coldenknows knight, Georg
<pb facs="tcp:25604:17"/> Hume of Weddirburne, Alexander Hume of Hulton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall, Patrick Hume appeirand of Ayton, Patrick Cok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne tutor of Langton, Iames Seton of Tullibody, &amp; M. Thomas Cranſton of Moreiſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, within the bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of our ſhyrifdome of Barwicke or Mers. William Ker of Cesfurde, Walter Scott of Branxholme, George Dowglas of Bonjedburgh, Iohn Crankſton of that ilk and Andro Ker of Fadounſide, within the boundis of our ſhyrifdom of Roxburgh or Teuiotdail. William L. Hay of Ȝeſter, Iohn Stewart of Tracquair, William Twedy of Drummelȝer and Patrick Murray of Faw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lahill, within the boundis of our ſhyrifdoms of Selkirk and Peblis. Iohn L. Hammilton, William earle of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus, Iames L. Someruile, Iames Maxwell of Calder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Iohn Stewart of Mynto, and Iames Hamilton of Liberton, within the boundis of our ſhyrifdome of Lanerk or Cliddiſdale. Lodovike Duke of Lennox, Iames earle of Glencarne, Robert L. Semple, George Buchannane of that ilk, Iohn Schaw of Grenok, Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Edmondſton of Duntreith &amp; Humfrey Colhoun of Lus, within the boundis of the Lennox &amp; our ſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifdom of Renfrew. Robert maiſter of Eglinton, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas L. Boyd, Iohn Blair of that ilke, &amp; Thomas Crau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furde of Iordanhil, within the bounds of our bayliery of Cunningham. Hew Campbel of Teorinȝean, Iohn Wallace of Cragy, Andro L. Vchiltree and William Craufurde of Lochnoreis, within the boundis of our baylierie of Kyle. Iohn Kennedy of Blairquhan, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Kennedy of Bargany and Iohn Cathcart of Carl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, within the boundis of our baylierie of Carrict. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander Stewarte of Garlers, Vthrid Makdougall of Garthland and ſchir Patricke Vaus of Barnbarrouch
<pb facs="tcp:25604:18"/> within the bounds of our ſhyrifdom of Wigton, Iohn Gordon of Lochinvar, Thomas Mackclellan of Bom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie, and Iames Lidderdale of ſainct Marie Ile within the boundis of our ſtewartrie of Kirkcudbright. Iohn L. Hamilton, Iames Dowglas of Torthorald, and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Greirſon of Lag, within the bounds of our ſhyrif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Drumfreis. Robert L. Sanquhar, Iames Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas of Drumlangrig, and Roger Kirkpatrick of Cloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn, within the Sanquhar, or ouer part of Nithiſdale. Iames Iohnſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Dunskelly, Charles Murray of Cok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pule &amp; Robert Iohnſon Laird of Neubie, within our ſtewartrie of Annanderdale. Archibald earl of Argile and his curators, within the bounds of our ſhyrifdome of Argile. Angus Mackconeil of Dunniveg &amp; Glennis Lauchlane Makclaine of Dowart, Donald Makco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neill Gorme of Slait, and Donald Mackcloid of Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, within the boundis of the Ilis. Attoure the ſaidis Lordis of our ſecreit Counſaill, heiring ſundrie bruits and rumors, aſweill offoreine as inteſtine plattis and preparations, for the trouble of the true and Chriſtian religion preſently profeſſed within our realme, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling of our eſtate and ſtanding, depending thairvp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, baith hauing the ſame ſelfe friends and common enemies, and ſubject to the like euent of ſtanding and decay: Hes thocht meit for preuenting of the danger threatned hereby, aſweill to the ane as to the vther. that firſt of all, the godly and weill affected perſons our gud ſubjects ſalbe knawne and diſcernit fra tham that are of a contrair diſpoſition, and to this effect, the ſaids Lords hes giuen and granted, &amp; be thir preſents giues and grantis full power and commiſſion, expreſſe bidding and charge to the perſons vnderwritten, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:25604:18"/> ane of thame within the boundis particularly limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat to tham as follows. They are to ſay, Thomas Swin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Henrye Coluile and Iohn Dunnone within the bounds of our ſhyrifdom of Ork nay. M. William Paip M. Robert Innes, William Gray ȝounger, Maſt. Iohn Robertſon, M. George Monro, M. Robert Williamſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and M. Thomas Howieſon, within the boundis of our ſhyrifdomes of Innernes and Cromarty. M. Robert Rait within the bounds of our ſhyrifdome of Narne. M. Iohn Keith miniſter at Duffus, M. Alexander Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas miniſter at Elgin, &amp; Iohn Foreſter miniſter at Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, within the bounds of our ſhyrifdomes of Elgin &amp; Fores. M. William Strauchauchin, M. Iames Duff &amp; M. George Nicolſon, within the boundes of our ſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifdome of Bamff. M. Peter Blackburne, Iohn Strau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauchin, Iames Reid and Abraham Sibbald within the boundis of our ſhyrifdome of Aberdeine. M. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro Myln, M. William Lisk &amp; M. Alexander Arbuth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net within the boundes of our ſhyrifdome of Kincar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din. M. Iames Meluin, M. Paule Fraſair, William Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteſon, M. Iames Nicolſon, M. Henrie Guthree, M. Henry Duncane, Iohn Foullarton and M. Thomas Ramſey, within the bounds of our ſhyrifdome of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair. M. William Glas, M. William Rynd, Alexander Ȝoung, M. Archibald Moncreiff &amp; M. William Rowe within the boundes of our ſhyrifdome of Perth, Stor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>month and Dunkeld. M. Andro Ȝoung M. William Striuiling and Alexander Fergy within the bounds of our ſtewartries of Stratherne, Menteith and diocie of Dunblane. Iohn Dykis, Robert Rait &amp; M. Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Wallace, within the bounds of our ſhyrifdoms of Clackmannane and Kinros, M. Thomas Buchannane,
<pb facs="tcp:25604:19"/> M. Andro Moncreiff, M. Iames Meluin and M. Adam Mitchell within the bounds of our ſhyrifdom of Fiff. Iohn Dunkeſon, M. Alexander Leuingſton and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro Foreſter, within the boundes of our ſhyrifdom of Striuiling. Patrick Kenlo quhy, M. Iames Law, and M Robert Cornwel, within the bounds of our ſhirifdom of Lynlithqw. M. Robert Bruce. M. Patrick Simſon &amp; M. Michaell Cranſton, within the boundis of our ſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifdome of Edinburgh. M. Adam Iohnſton. Iohn He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reis and Iames Gibſon within Dalkeith. William San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon, M. Cuthbert Boncle, M. Thomas Mackgye &amp; M. Iames Carmichaell, within the Conſtabularie of Hadington and Dumbar. Dauid Hume, Iohn Clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perton and Robert French, within our ſhyrifdome of Berwicke or Mers. M. Andro Clayhillis, M. William Auchmowty, Ceorge Iohnſton, William Balfour &amp; M Iohn Knox, within our ſhyrifdom of Roxburgh or Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viotdaill. M. Archibald Dowglas miniſter at Peblis, M Iohn Welſhe, miniſter at Selkirk and William Sander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon miniſter at Innerletham, within the bounds of the Foreſt and Tweddall. M. Iohn Dauidſon, M. Robert Lindſay, and M. Andro Haye, within the boundes of Cliddiſdail or Lanerk. M. Thom. Iak, M. Andro Knox, and M. Patrick Walkinſhaw, within the boundis of the Lennox &amp; our ſhyrifdome of Renfrew. M. Alexander Sk imgeour, M. Alexander Wrato<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; M. Robert Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ky, within our baylierie of Cuningham. Iohn Porter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field, M. Iohn Inglis &amp; M. Peter Primrois, within our bayliery of Kyle. Iohn Makcorne &amp; William Ȝoung within our baylierie of Carict. M. Ninian Makcle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quhen and Iohn Ȝong within our ſhyrifdom of Wig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton. M. Iames Hamilton and M. Dauid Blyith, within
<pb facs="tcp:25604:19"/> our Stewartry of Kirkcudbright. M. Hew Foullarton and William Thomeſon, within our ſhyrifdome of Drumfreis. M. Iames Bryſon and Iohn Foullarton, within the Sanquhar or ouer part of Nythiſdale. Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Gairdner, within Annanderdal. M. Neil Camp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell within our ſhyrifdome of Argile. All and ſyndrie Earles, Lords, Barons, freehalders, gentlemen, inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of our burrowis, and vther our lieges quhatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, of quhat ranke &amp; degree that euer they be of: To cal &amp; conuene before the ſaids Miniſters, be their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue letters or meſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, at quhatſoeuer places &amp; dayes they ſhall thinke expedient, &amp; they require tham to gif the confeſſion of their faith, together with their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions theirto, to the general Band maid &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriued already be vs, &amp; certain of our eſtaits, touching the maintenance &amp; defence of the ſaide true religion, our perſon &amp; eſtait, &amp; withſtanding of al forreine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations &amp; forces, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to the trouble thairof. And incaſe any perſons ſo required diſobey, that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Gods word proceed to admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; finding tham obſtinate, cauſe the cenſures of the Kirk be vſed againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as enemies to god, vs, &amp; to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monweal of this thair natiue countrie. And that the ſaids Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters craue the concurrence of the noblemen, Barrons and gentlemen, within the bounds particularly aboue written for the better execution of the premiſes. OVR VVILL IS heirfoir, and we charge ȝou ſtraitly &amp; That incontinent thir our letters ſene ȝee paſſe &amp; in our name &amp; authoritie make publication heirof, be open proclamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the mercat croces of the head burrows of our realm, &amp; vthers places neidful, quhair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe nane pretende ignorance of the ſame: As alſo
<pb facs="tcp:25604:20"/> that ȝee command &amp; charge the Noble men, Barons Miniſters and vthers foreſaids, to accept vpon thame our commiſſion geuen to euerie ane of thame, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner perticularly aboue mentioned, and to report thair diligence touching the execution therof, to the Clerk of our ſecreit Counſaill, betwix and the twentie day of May nixt to come, vnder the paine of rebellion &amp; putting of thame to our Horne, with certification to thame and thay faillȝie, they falbe denunceitrebels and put to our Horne: and all thair mouable gudes eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheit and inbrocht, to our vſe, for their contemption. And ſicklike that ȝee command and charge all &amp; ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie our liegeis, to readily anſwere, intende, obeye, concur, fortifie and aſſiſt our ſaid commiſſioners in the execution of the premiſſes, &amp; to doe, nor attempt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to thair hinderance, as they and ilkane of tham will anſwer to vs vpon thair obedience &amp; allegeance, and vnder all hieſt paine, crime and offence, that they may commit and incur againſt vs, in that behalf, As ȝe wil anſwer to vs thair vpon. The quhilk to do, we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to you conjunctly and ſeuerally, our full power be thir our letters, deliuering thame be you duely exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute, and indorſate againe to the bearer. Giuen vnder our ſignet, At Edinburgh the ſaxt of Marche, and of our reigne the xxiij. ȝeir, 1589.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Per Actum ſecreti conſilij. I. ANDRO</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25604:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
